Preliminary Inventory of the Makerere University Slides, 1969
Hoover Institution Archives
Makerere University Slides,
1969
72041
Makerere University
4 slide boxes (0.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Illustrates the history of Christianity in East Africa. Prepared by the Department of Religious Studies and the Audio-Visual Aids Center of Makerere University, Kampala, Uganda.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Christianity--Africa, East--Pictorial works.; Africa.; Africa, East.; Slides (Photography)
Notes on Slide Sets
These slides are arranged in sets of twelve, and each set is intended to be complete within itself, and to provide sufficient teaching material for one session. Twelve slides may seem very few to shew in one session, but a mistake frequently made is to shew too many slides at one time. Each picture is intended to be a peg on which teaching and discussion can be hung, and it is often useful to run through a set of slides a second time, getting a student to make the comments on the picture, or to question his fellow pupils.
The notes which follow will need to be supplemented by the teacher, but it is hoped that enough information is given to indicate why the sets have been made up as they are.
The sets could be used in a number of ways. They could be used as illustrative material for the initial teaching of a subject; or they could be used for revision purposes. Other combinations of pictures could be made, or one set amplified from another or with the teacher's own slides.
These slide sets do not pretend to cover the history of Christianity in East Africa exhaustively, and there are many aspects which are ommitted altogether. The Department of Religious Studies is very grateful to all those who have helped to collect the material used here, and asks those who use it to help collect further useful illustrations.
List of Slides
- INTRODUCTORY SET.
  This set of slides is included as a reminder that Christianity has had a continuous presence in Africa since its earliest days, and is not simply a nineteenth century importation.
  - Columns in the church at Apollonia, Cyrenaica. North Africa formed part of the Roman Empire, and was studded with cities built in the Roman style, many of whose ruins can still be seen. When Christianity became the religion of the Empire after Constantine, large churches were multiplied, often built in the style of Roman public buildings. In a number of places the marble columns of former pagan temples were reused, as is possibly the case here. The second half of the third century saw the beginnings of a mass conversion to Christianity., I 2.
  - An aerial photograph of the ruins of Timgad, which shews clearly the ground-plan of the Christian basilica, ending in an apse, around which would be seated the Bishop and his clergy. Timgad was the greatest Donatist stronghold in Southern Numidia, and at the end of the 4th C the seat of the powerful Donatist bishop, Optatus, who was probably responsible for building one of the largest Cathedrals in Roman Africa, and a richly decorated baptistery., I 2.
  - This is the earliest known portrait of St Augustine of Hippo. It comes from a 6th C fresco in the Lateran palace, Rome., I 3.
  - Coptic Christian textiles. Whereas the rise of Islam in the 7th C was virtually to wipe out Christianity in much of North Africa, in Egypt the Coptic Church, though reduced to a small minority, has nevertheless managed to survive down to the present. But the initiative in art passed largely to the Muslims., I 4.
  - To the south of Egypt, above the First Cataract, lay Nubia. Christianity probably began to filter into Nubia in the 3rd C although the official conversion did not take place until the 6th C. This picture shews a pagan temple converted into a Christian church on the typical basilican plan, with seats for the clergy round the apse., I 5.
  - The Cathedral at Faras has recently been excavated by a team of Polish archaeologists working under the auspices of U.N.E.S.C.O. since it was threatened with inundation by the waters of the High Aswan Dam. The archaeologists were amazed to discover a building whose walls were covered with frescoes, many in a Byzantine style of painting. One of the finest is shewn here - the Archangel Michael is protecting the three Israelites in the burning fiery furnace in the story from the book of Daniel., I 6.
  - Also depicted on the walls of Faras Cathedral are kings, queens and bishops. Bishop Petros, shewn here, was Metropolitan from 973 -?999, the last of four bishops to hold the title of Metropolitan, whose episcopacies lasted about a century. The painting shews clearly that he was of Nubian, not Egyptian, stock., I 7.
  - The conversion of Ethiopia took place in the 4th C. Later fugitive Syrian monks, Monophysites fleeing from persecution by the Orthodox, entered Ethiopia, and by their teaching and introduction of monasticism, set Ethiopian Christianity on a firmer footing. This picture shews the Nine Saints, as they are called, who were reputed to have gone to different parts of the country spreading Christian teaching., I 8.
  - The Scriptures and liturgy were translated into Ge'ez, the local language, and although this is no longer intelligible to modern Ethiopians unless they are specially trained, it is still used in the liturgy and studied by the clergy. Many churches possess ancient mss books like this one here, which are richly decorated and beautifully written, and the Ethiopian Department of Antiquities is trying to conserve these., I 9.
  - Among the oldest surviving churches in Ethiopia are the rockhewn churches of Lalibela. This picture shews the church of St George. Many country churches today are built of mud and wattle and the most common shape is circular, but even small churches may possess rich mss and vestments and other treasures., I 10.
  - In the 15th C new contacts were made between Africa and the Christian world when Portuguese adventurers tried to find a way round the Muslim-ruled lands to the far East with its valuable trade. They undertook the responsibility of evangelising the peoples with whom they came into contact, though they did not always fulfil this obligation. Their most successful venture in evangelism in Africa was in the Kingdom of the Kongo (in modern Angola) and Christianity lasted here for about 300 years. In this picture an attempt is made to shew the Portuguese arriving in Kingo, and the first king to become a Christian, receiving baptism - he was called Johannes, that being also the name of the king of Portugal., I 11.
  - The Kongo kingdom was slowly reduced in size and power, and the Portuguese were unable to keep up a regular supply of missionary priests because of their many commitments in Africa and the Far East, and because of sickness and death. By the 19th C when missionary work received a new lease of life, little remained of the once-flourishing Christianity of the Kingo. But crucifixes like this were found, being used as hunting charms by people who had forgotten their meaning. Only in Egypt and Ethiopia had the church remained strong., I 12.
- UGANDA.
  - SET I. EARLY DAYS.
    Picture credits:
    U3, 5, 7, 8, 10, 11: White Fathers Archives, Rome.
    U4, 9: Rev. Fr Payeur and White Fathers.
    U12: Miss C. Franklin and Bishop Tucker College, Mukono.
    U2: Miss M.I.N. Lule and Church of Uganda Literature Bureau.
    U10: Fransiscan Missionary Sisters for Africa.
    - When the explorer H.M. Stanley visited the court of Kabaka Mutesa in 1875 he found Islam' being taught. He therefore left a convert of the Universities' Mission to Central Africa, Dallington Scopion Maftaa, who was one of his servants, to instruct the Kabaka in Christianity until Christian missionaries could arrive. Having a little knowledge of English, Dallington wrote a number of letters for the Kabaka which are still extant, including this one to General Gordon., U1.
    - Within a few years of the arrival of the Anglican Church Missionary Society and the Roman Catholic White Fathers, Mutesa died and was succeeded by his son, Mwanga. For a complex variety of reasons, basically political, the royal pages who were among the first converts to Christianity, found themselves the target of persecution which reached its climax when 32 were burnt at Namugongo on June 3, 1886. This picture shews some of the martyrs, tied in mats of dried reeds as was the custom, being thrown on the execution pyre., U2.
    - Among the martyrs there was also a group from Rityana, whose leader was Noe Mawagali. His sister, seeing her brother done to death, told the executioners that she too was a Christian, but instead of being killed she was taken by the royal legate who wanted her as one of his wives. She was imprisoned when she refused him, and was redeemed by Pere Lourdel. She is the woman in this picture, clothed in traditional bark-cloth dress., U3.
    - In 1888 further trouble befell the Christians when, after a coup d'etat they were all driven into exile by the Muslim party. The missionaries were sent south of Lake Victoria, and this led to the founding of the Catholic Mission at Bukumi in Sukumaland. This picture shews the group of orphans and redeemed slaves for whom the mission cared, in charge of the first two Baganda girls who acted as catechists., U4.
    - After the Christian Baganda had fought their way back to power in 1889, Stanislaus Mugwanya, pictured here with his wife and family, became leader of the Catholic party, and one of the three most powerful chiefs in the kingdom., U5.
    - His Anglican counterpart was Apolo Kagwa, for many years Katikiro or chief minister of Buganda. Both these men used their high position to further the progress of Christianity., U6.
    - Because of the influence of chiefs in the kingdom states, the missions made great efforts to win their allegiance. Here is Msgr Guillermain, Vicar-Apostolic from 1895/6, being received at a chief's headquarters., U7.
    - From 1890 onwards people flocked to the missions to be instructed in the new religion. Catechists were soon being widely used to give elementary instruction for baptism, and to teach reading. Literacy was in great demand, and was normally a requirement for baptism. This catechist is shewn teaching letters and syllables from a reading sheet pinned up out of doors. Often a small mud and wattle chapel was used for prayers and catechism classes during the week, and for prayers on Sunday if the place was too far from the mission to attend church there., U8.
    - The missions tried to ensure adequate pre-baptismal instruction, the White Fathers insisting on a four-year catechumenate for a long time, the last six months of which had to be spent at the mission. Children of Christian parents were brought to the mission for first communion instruction. Here is a group of such children feasting after they have made their first communion., U9.
    - When conditions in Uganda became more settled, women missionaries also arrived, ladies of the C.M.S. in 1896, White Sisters in 1899, and in 1902 Fransiscan Sisters arrived to assist the Mill Hill Fathers. This English and Dutch society came to Uganda in 1895 and worked in the Eastern part of the country. This picture shews two Fransiscan Sisters with their first school at Nsambya in 1903, One of the two is Mother Kevin who worked in Uganda for many years, and was the initiator of many developments in the education and professional training of Catholic girls., U10.
    - From 1902 - 10 the missions found themselves engaged in helping victims of a sleeping sickness epidemic which was particularly serious during these years. Little could be done for the sufferers medically once they had contracted the disease, but the worst hit areas were evacuated, and many sleeping-sickness patients cared for in mission-run settlements such as this., U11.
    - A village church and some of the members of its congregation. Small churches like this were built all over the country, usually at the headquarters of a chief, and were in the charge of a catechist. These churches were the foundations of primary education in Uganda. If the catechist were able he would teach a little arithmetic and writing as well as giving religious instruction and teaching reading., U12.
  - SET II. CHRISTIANITY SPREADS.
    U14, 17: Miss C. Franklin and Bishop Tucker College
    U15: Fr Payeur and White Fathers
    U16, 20: White Fathers Archives and Katigondo Seminary.
    U18, 24: Verona Fathers
    U22: Schofield Collection
    U23: Miss P. Cave-Brown-Cave.
    - After the Christian revolution in Buganda requests were received from chiefs for Christian teaching to be given at their headquarters, and because of Buganda's diplomatic contacts whith neighbouring kingdoms, their rulers also were persuaded to ask for, or at least accept, Christian teachers. Among the first to do so was Kasagama, king of Toro, who was baptised by the C.M.S. in 1896. He is seen in the centre of this picture. He did much to encourage the spread of Protestant Christianity in Toro, persuading his followers to learn at the mission and helping to break down people's fears of the mission hospital when this was established. Behind him stands Hana Kageye, an aristocratic and influential lady who, together with his wife and mother, was an active Christian. In 1902 Hana Kageye went to Ankole for a time to help instruct the royal ladies there who lived in seclusion and were virtually inaccesible to the missionaries. The others in the picture are, U13.
    - When a request such as Kasagama's was received it was seldom possible for a European missionary to be made available at once, and African missionaries were usually the pioneers. A catechist is here seen setting out with his personal possessions rolled up in his sleeping mat, and his Bible in his hand. He was paid a tiny salary, and in the case of the C.M.S. this was usually collected from the local church members., U14.
    - Later, when the catechist had given some initial teaching, and had prepared some converts for baptism, a mission might be established if the centre was important enough. The missionaries would spend a good deal of their time travelling around the outstations, examining candidates for baptism, helping the catechists, and administering the sacraments., U15.
    - Here a group of White Sisters is seen setting out to make a new foundation. The work of women missionaries was essential if the women were to be taught, and Christian family life established. The Sisters and women missionaries of the C.M.S. taught women and girls homecraft as well and literacy and religion, established girls' schools, and nursed in mission hospitals., U16.
    - Soon after 1900 Christianity began to reach Northern and Eastern Uganda. Chiefs in these areas had a differently based authority from those in the Bantu kingdoms, and were usually reluctant to become Christians. However, permission would usually be granted for some of their children to attend the mission schools, and government encouraged this as it wanted literate chiefs trained. This is an Acoli chief with some of his household. The C.M.S. entered Acoli in 1904 and the Verona Fathers in 1910., U17.
    - This picture shews mass being said outside the first Catholic Church in Gulu. The Verona Fathers had for long been trying to reach northern Uganda by way of the Nile, but terrible losses through disease, and later the Mahdi revolt had prevented them from doing so in the 19th century. Their work spread from West Nile to Karamoja. The C.M.S. were joined by the Africa Inland Mission which worked in West Nile from 1917, and the Bible Churchmen's Missionary Society which worked in Karamoja from 1930., U18.
    - Christianity first reached Lango from Bunyoro in 1905. The Mukama (king) of Bunyoro was a zealous Christian, a convert of the C.M.S. Bunyoro had long been on friendly terms with Lango, and teachers were sent at the request of Odora of Aduku in South Lango. The Mukama also sent a present of drums to be used for calling the people to Church, and when the original drums wore out, new ones were given in 1917, the ones which appear in this picture., U19.
    - From quite early days women teachers were also at work. One such was Hana Kageye, seen in U13. From 1910 onwards, African religious sisters were sent in groups of five or six to help in the parishes. From 1914 onwards they worked in Ankole, Bunyoro, Toro and Busoga as well as Buganda. Their main work was to teach catechism to children, and prepare children for their first communion. When secular education gained in importance, the Anglicans no longer trained women specifically for church work until quite recently., U20.
    - Although evangelists from Buganda were the first teachers and catechists in a number of areas, these soon began to produce catechists of their own. Paulo Byabusakuzi has been an Anglican teacher in Toro since 1901, working in many different parts of the country. Children of catechists had a good chance of education, and a number became priests and leaders. Paulo Byabusakuzi's son, Timothy Bazarabuza, was Uganda's first High Commissioner in London., U21.
    - Canon Apolo Kivebulaya is one of the best known Ugandan missionaries. In 1895 he went to Toro, and from there on to Mboga in what is now the Congo. Later he went to the pygmies of the Ituri Forest, and was the first to reduce their language to writing when he translated St Mark's Gospel for them. He was greatly loved for his kindliness and humility. Like his Catholic counterpart, Yohana Kitagana who pioneered in western Ankole and Kigezi, he remained unmarried in order to be freer for his work, and gave away almost everything he came to possess. Kivebulaya died in 1933., U22.
    - The Rev. Petero Lukungu spent most of his life working in Teso and Acoli. He is shewn here with the Rev. S. Okwir, soon after the latter had been ordained deacon. Okwir was the first Anglican from northern Uganda to be ordained. Lukungu was responsible for founding the Anglican church in Kumam., U23.
    - This picture shews Bishop Kihangire outside Gulu Cathedral after his consecration in 1963 (contrast picture U18). At first Bishop of Hoima, he was translated to Gulu in 1969. Developments in the churches in the north have recently necessitated the creation of new Anglican and Catholic bishoprics, and the appointment of several new African bishops., U24.
  - SET III. THE GROWTH OF CHRISTIAN LEADERSHIP.
    Picture Credits:
    U25, 32: Miss C. Franklin and Bishop Tucker College.
    U28, 29, 34: White Fathers
    U30, 33: White Fathers and Katigondo Seminary.
    U31: Mrs Richards (Dr. Carabtree)
    U35: Dr. J.E. Church
    U36: Mother Vincent
    - After the Christian Revolution of 1889 there was little prospect of political advancement in Uganda unless a man were literate, and unless he received Christian instruction from the missions. There was an enormous desire for books and Africans themselves quickly began to respond to the demand for literature. Apolo Kagwa was the first of many who wrote histories, volumes of moral admonition, and political pamphlets. This picture shews the queue outside the C.M.S. Bookshop at Mengo when a new consignment of books has arrived. The picture was taken in 1905., U25.
    - Very important Christian leaders in the early days were the Christian chiefs. This picture shows Alexis Sebowa, county chief of Buddu from 1892 until his death in 1937. After Stanislaus Mugwanya, he was the leading Catholic. He gave the land on which Bukalasa Seminary is built, and later the land for the headquarters of the Bannabikira (Daughters of Mery). He tried to uphold Christian ideals of marriage, and to see that his sub-chiefs did so too, and, like many chiefs, employed a catechist to lead prayers for his household, and instruct them in Christianity., U26.
    - Yakobo Okwerede of Teso is a leading Anglican layman, and has also been a county chief (he is the older man in this picture). Baptised in 1911, he worked as a church teacher before being made a chief in 1922. From 1920 - 1954 he was a member first of the parish council and then of the diocesan synod, and though now retired, still gives a lead in church affairs., U27.
    - Many catechists had only a minimum of training, but those whose work was promising were picked for special courses. This slide shows St Joseph's School for Catechists at Bikira in south west Uganda (Buddu). Anglican catechists were trained by the local mission in the earlier stages, but a more advanced course was given at Mukono. Catechists usually were accompanied by their wives during their training, and the wives also received teaching in child caree, homecraft and religion., U28.
    - As early as 1892 a group of Ugandans went to Malta and North Africa to train as brothers with the White Fathers Mission, and the first group is shown here. One of them, Brother Tobie Kizza, who worked in many parts of Uganda died only in 1961. In 1927 an indigenous congrogation of brothers was founded, the Brothers of St. Charles Lwanga (Bannakaroli)., U29.
    - The first noviciate for religious sisters was opened in 1908, and the members of the new congregation were trained by the White Sisters. Mother Mechtilde, foundress of this congregation is seen here surrounded by some of the Bannabikira whom she had trained. The Bannabikira gained its independence in 1924 when they first elected their own Superior General. Since then, several tother groups of sisters have been founded, and their total numbers in 1969 were c. 1,300., U30.
    - Uganda was fortunate in having among the missionaries men of vision who were convinced that an African-led Church could be a reality in Uganda soon. The Right Rev. A.R. Tucker, Bishop from 1891 - 1911 was a strong believer in the principles laid down by Henry Venn that the aim of missions was to establish churches which would be self-governing, self-supporting and self-extending. He ordained the first Ugandan clergy in 1893. He is seen here with Dr and Mrs Cook standing behind him. These two came to Uganda in 1896 and established Mengo Hospital, which gave the first medical training to Africans in Uganda., U31.
    - The Anglican Theological collége at Mukono, here seen in process of being built, was aptly named after Bishop Tucker., U32.
    - Because of the different educational standards required, it took longer to train the first Catholic clergy, but a seminary was founded in 1893, and the first priests ordained in 1913. Here the seminarians are having their midday meal. The perseverance of some of those who entered the seminary in its earliest days, and went right through to ordination, was one reason for the comparatively early success achieved in Uganda., U33.